Now it's time to talk for a minute about tokens.
이제 토큰에 대해 잠깐 얘기해 보죠
Tokens are the individual units which get passed into a model.
토큰은 모델로 전환되는 개별 유닛이에요.
In the early days of building neural networks, one of the things that you'd see quite often is neural
신경망을 구축하던 초기에는 캐릭터마다 훈련된
networks that were trained character by character.
신경망을 자주 사용했어요
So you would have a model which would take a series of individual characters, and it would be trained
일련의 캐릭터를 구성하는 모델이 있어야 해요 그리고 훈련해서 가장
such that it would predict the most likely next character, given the characters that have come before.
유력한 다음 캐릭터를 예측하는 거죠 이전의 캐릭터를 고려해서요
That was a particular technique, and in some ways it had a lot of benefits.
특별한 기술이었고 어떤 면에선 장점도 많았어요
It meant that the number of possible inputs was a limited number, just the number of possible letters
가능한 입력 수의 숫자는 제한된 숫자라는 의미였죠 가능한 알파벳 문자와
of the alphabet and some symbols.
일부 기호의 숫자요
And so that meant that it had a very manageable vocab size.
그래서 다루기 쉬운 단어가 많이 생겼죠
And it needed to its weights could didn't didn't need to worry about too many different possibilities
그 무게는 입력에 대한 너무 많은 가능성을 걱정할
for the inputs.
필요가 없었죠
But the challenge with it was that it meant that there was so much required from the model in terms
하지만 문제는 그 모델에 요구되는 게 너무 많다는 거였어요 일련의 다른
of understanding how a series of different characters becomes a word, and all of the intelligence associated
캐릭터들이 어떻게 단어로 변하는지 이해해야 했고 단어에 담긴 의미와 관련된 모든
with the meaning behind a word had to be captured within the weights of the model, and that was expecting
지성이 모델의 무게에 담겨야 했는데 그건 모델 자체에 너무 많은
too much from the model itself.
걸 요구하는 거였죠
And so we then went to almost the other extreme where neural networks, these models were trained of
그다음에는 거의 다른 극한으로 갔어요 각 단어의 정보를 훈련한
each individual possible word.
신경망 모형들이었죠
So you would build something called the vocab, which is like like the sort of the dictionary, the
그래서 단어 선택이라는 걸 만들어요 사전 같은 건데 가능한
index of all the possible words.
모든 단어의 인덱스죠
And then each possible word a token could be any one of these possible words.
각각의 단어는 토큰이 될 수 있어요 이 중 아무 단어나 될 수 있죠
So that meant that the the model itself could start to understand that each individual word had a different
즉, 모델 자체가 각 단어의 의미가 다르다는 걸 이해하기 시작했다는 거죠
meaning, rather than having to to appreciate how a sequence of characters would have a meaning.
캐릭터의 연속적인 의미를 이해하는 대신에요
So that was a good thing.
그건 좋은 일이었죠
But the trouble was that it resulted in an enormous vocab.
하지만 문제는 그 결과로 엄청난 어휘가 나왔다는 거죠
You needed to have a vocab the size of all of the possible words.
가능한 모든 단어를 합친 단어가 필요했어요
And of course, there are so many possible words because there are also names of places and people.
가능한 단어가 아주 많아요 장소와 사람들의 이름도 있으니까요
And so there had to be special tokens for unknown words.
그래서 모르는 단어를 위한 특별한 증표가 있어야 했죠
And that that caused some limitations.
그래서 한계가 생겼죠
Rare words had to be omitted, special places had to be omitted.
희귀한 단어와 특별한 장소는 생략해야 했죠
And so that caused some some some some oddness.
그래서 좀 이상한 일이 생겼어요
Um, and then around the time of the of GPT uh, a discovery was made a breakthrough that that there
그러다 GPT가 개발될 무렵 돌파구를 찾았습니다 양극단 사이에 적절한 매체가 있다는
was a sort of happy medium between these two extremes, rather than trying to train a model based on
사실이었죠 캐릭터별로 모델을 훈련하고 그것들을 조합해
individual characters and need it to learn how to combine them to form a word.
단어를 만드는 법을 배우는 대신에요
And rather than trying to say that each word is a different token, you could take chunks of letters,
각각의 단어가 다른 토큰이라고 말하는 것보다는 하나의 글자를 모아서 완전한 단어를
chunks that would that would sometimes form a complete word and sometimes part of a word, and call
만들거나 단어의 일부를 토큰으로 만드는 것이 더 좋을 것 같습니다.
it a token, and train the model to take a series of tokens and output tokens based on the tokens that
그렇게 해서 전달되는 토큰에 기반하여 일련의 토큰과 출력 토큰을 만들도록 하는 거죠.
And this had a number of interesting benefits.
이 방법에는 흥미로운 장점이 많아요
One of them is that because you're breaking things down into tokens, you could also handle things like
그중 하나는 토큰으로 나누기 때문에 장소의 이름이나 정식 이름
names of places and proper names.
같은 것도 다룰 수 있다는 거죠
They would just be more fragments of tokens.
그저 패의 조각에 불과할 뿐이죠
And then there was a second interesting effect, which is that it meant that it was good at handling
두 번째 흥미로운 효과는 단어 스템 처리에도 좋다는 겁니다
word stems, or times when you'd have the same beginning of a word and multiple potential endings that
혹은 단어 시작 부분이 같아 여러 잠재적 결말을 하나의 토큰에 인코딩하고
would be encoded into one token, followed by a few second tokens.
몇 개의 토큰으로 이어질 때요
And that meant that the sort of underlying meaning of what you're trying to say could be easily represented
즉, 말하고자 하는 것의 기저에 깔린 의미는 모델 내에서 쉽게 표현될 수 있다는 것입니다.
inside the model, because the tokens had the same kind of structure that might have sounded a bit abstract.
왜냐하면 토큰은 약간 추상적으로 들릴 수도 있는 구조로 구성되어 있기 때문이죠.
Let me make that a bit more real for you.
좀 더 현실적인 비트로 바꿔드리죠
So GPT, OpenAI actually provides a tool which is a platform openai.com slash tokenizer, and it lets
GPT, OpenAI는 플랫폼 OpenAI라는 도구를 제공하죠 comp/토큰라이저입니다 텍스트를
you put in some text and see visually how that text is turned into tokens.
입력하면 어떻게 토큰으로 바뀌는지 볼 수 있죠
And so I took a particular sentence, an important sentence for my class of AI engineers.
그래서 한 문장을 선택했습니다 우리 인공지능 엔지니어 학급에게는 중요한 문장이죠
And you can see that GPT tokenized that.
GPT가 그걸 토큰화한 걸 볼 수 있죠
That's the verb that we use when we're turning from words into tokens.
단어를 증표로 바꿀 때 사용하는 동사죠
And it highlights in colors how it turned that into tokens.
그게 어떻게 토큰이 됐는지 색으로 강조하죠
And in this case, because these are all common words, every one of these words mapped precisely to
이 경우에는 모두 흔한 단어라서 모든 단어가 토큰 하나에 정확히 그려져
one token.
있어요
So this is a clear example.
이게 확실한 예죠
You can see from the colors.
색깔을 보면 알 수 있죠
One other slightly interesting point to make that's that's important.
또 하나 흥미로운 점은 중요한 거예요
You see the way that some of these colored boxes, like the word for has a space in front of it.
색깔 있는 상자 몇 개가 앞에 공간이 있어요
It's like space.
우주 같아요
And then for is what's been tokenized.
그리고 for는 표시된 거죠
That's because the break between words is also meaningful when tokenizing.
왜냐하면 표기할 때도 단어 간격이 의미가 있거든요
That token represents the word for in isolation, like that beginning of word followed by the letters
저 토큰은 격리된 워드를 나타내요 워드의 시작 부분처럼요 그걸 위한 글자들이
for that is mapped to one token, the beginning of word for token, and so that that will maybe become
토큰의 시작 부분에 매핑되죠 토큰에 대한 워드의 시작 부분에요 그건 잠시 후에 좀 더 중요해질 거예요
But.
하지만요
But it's worth noting that the gap between words is included as part of a token.
하지만 단어 사이의 간격도 토큰의 일부로 포함된다는 걸 알아두세요
So let's take another example.
다른 예를 들어보죠
Now in this example, I'm coming up with a slightly more interesting sentence, an exquisitely handcrafted
이 예시에서는 좀 더 흥미로운 문장을 떠올려 봅니다 LM 위치크래프트
quip for my musterers of LM witchcraft.
몰이꾼들을 위한 정교한 수제 재담이죠
Now Musterers is, I believe, an invented word.
몰이꾼이란 말은 지어낸 말일 거예요
As you'll see, the red squiggly underline shows that it's not a true word.
여기 보시면 빨간 구불구불한 선이 가짜라는 걸 알 수 있어요
And let's see how the tokenization has happened down here.
어떻게 토큰화가 이루어졌는지 보죠
So you'll see that that four is still here as one word, uh, with a beginning of token at the beginning
4는 여전히 한 단어로 여기 있는 게 보이시죠 토큰의 앞부분도요
But and so is an Anne at the start, but exquisitely has been broken up into multiple tokens.
하지만 앤도 마찬가지예요 하지만 여러 토큰으로 정교하게 나뉘어 있죠
Exquisitely.
아주 정교하게요
And that shows how when you've got a rare word, it doesn't have that word as a single word in its vocab.
희귀한 단어를 쓰면 그 단어가 한 단어로 안 쓰인다는 걸 알 수 있죠
And so it had to break it into multiple tokens, but it's still able to pass it in.
여러 개의 토큰으로 나눠야 했지만 여전히 전달할 수 있었죠
And now look at that word handcrafted.
그 단어는 수제품이에요
You can see that it also doesn't have that in its vocab as a single token, but it's able to break that
보다시피 단일 토큰이라는 단어에도 그게 없어요 하지만 그걸
into hand and craft it.
쪼개서 만들 수 있죠
And that does kind of reflect the, the, the, the meaning in a way it does get across that it can.
그게 그 의미를 반영해요 어떤 면에서는요 Get it의 의미요
It's combined from these two hand and crafted.
두 가지를 수작업으로 합친 거예요
And you can see as well that the crafted token does not include a beginning of sentence.
보다시피 만들어진 토큰은 문장의 시작을 포함하지 않죠
So it's a token that represents a word that that has crafted in the middle of it.
중간에 만들어진 단어를 상징하는 토큰인 셈이죠
That's what that token reflects.
그게 그 토큰의 의미죠
You'll see that quip isn't there at all.
그런 농담은 전혀 안 통해요
It got broken into and it uh, and then you'll see Masteries.
누군가 침입했고 마스터시스 사진도 있어요
And this is a good example of what I was saying about word stems.
단어 줄기에 대해 말씀드린 좋은 예죠
Masteries has been broken into master, which is after all, the the, the verb that we're going for
마스터는 마스터로 바뀌었는데 여기서 중요한 건 동사죠
here, someone who masters and then errs at the end as an extension to that word.
마스터를 익혔다가 마지막에 실수하는 사람요
Um, and so you can see that it's, it's able to reflect the meaning of what we're trying to say by
보다시피 우리가 말하려는 의미를 반영할 수 있어요 두 개의 토큰으로
breaking it into those two tokens, even though it's not a real word.
쪼개서요 진짜 단어는 아니지만요
And you can also see that witchcraft got broken into witch and craft, uh, which is also interesting.
마법과 공예가 섞여 들어간 것도 볼 수 있어요 이것도 흥미롭죠
Uh, and so, yeah, handcrafted.
네, 수공예품이에요
And master, as I say, you can see how the meaning is reflected there by the tokens.
스승님, 말씀드렸듯이 현극령에 그 의미가 반영돼 있죠
And hopefully this gives you some real insight into what it means to break something into tokens.
여러분이 이걸 통해 토큰으로 뭔가를 쪼개는 게 어떤 의미인지 깨달았으면 좋겠네요
So an interesting one here is to now show you this slightly more sophisticated example.
여기서 흥미로운 건 이 좀 더 복잡한 예시를 보여드리는 거예요
Uh, my favorite number, apparently 6534589793238462643383.
제가 좋아하는 숫자죠 6534589793238462643383이에요
Blah blah blah.
어쩌고저쩌고 말이죠
Uh, so, uh, it shows you that when you have something like this, of course, long numbers like pi
이 화면을 보면 이런 게 있을 때 파이처럼 긴 숫자는 토큰 하나로
are not going to map to one token.
대응하지 않아요
And in fact, what you see is happening here is that every series of three digit numbers is being mapped
여기서 벌어지는 일을 보면 모든 일련의 세 자리 숫자가 토큰 하나에 매핑되고
to one token.
있어요
And that's an interesting property.
흥미로운 자산이죠
It's actually a property of GPT two tokenizer, but many others don't have that many other cases.
사실 GPT 2 토큰라이저의 속성입니다 하지만 다른 많은 제품에는 그렇게 많은 케이스가 없죠
You'll see that things map to multiple tokens.
여러 개의 토큰을 가지고 있는 것을 볼 수 있어요.
Uh, so the generally speaking, there's a rule of thumb which is helpful to know to bear in mind when
일반적으로 토큰을 볼 때 명심해야 할 경험 법칙이
you're looking at tokens.
있어요
The rule of thumb generally is that on average, one token typically maps to about four characters.
경험 법칙에 따르면 토큰 하나는 보통 네 글자로 매핑이 돼요
And that means that a token is on average for normal English writing, it's about three quarters of
보통 영어 문학에서 토큰은 평균적으로 단어 4분의 3에 해당해요
One token maps to about 0.75 words.
토큰 한 장은 0개 정도고요 75단어요
And an easier way to think about that.
쉽게 생각할 수 있는 방법이죠
A better way to put it is that a thousand tokens is about 750 words.
쉽게 말하면 천 현은 750글자나 되죠 Put
So that's the mapping to have in your mind.
그게 여러분이 염두에 두셔야 할 지도예요
A thousand tokens is 750 words.
천 현은 750글자예요
And that means that the complete works of Shakespeare, for example, to make this real, to give a
셰익스피어 전작을 예로 들어 볼게요 예를 들어 현실적으로 보면 약
real example, that's about 900,000 words, apparently in the complete works of Shakespeare.
900,000단어로 된 셰익스피어 작품이죠
So about 1.2 million tokens, that is the size of the complete works of Shakespeare.
1명 정도요 200만 토큰이면 셰익스피어 작품 전집과 맞먹는 크기죠
Now, that refers to English.
영어를 말하는 거예요
If you're looking at things like math formulas, scientific terms and also code, then the token count
수학 공식이나 과학 용어, 코드 같은 것을 볼 때 토큰의 수는 훨씬 더 많습니다 여기에서
is much higher because obviously, as we saw here with numbers, things need to be broken into many
숫자들을 보았듯이 더 많은 토큰으로 쪼개져야 합니다 올바른
more tokens to incorporate Right symbols and stuff like that.
심볼 같은 것을 포함하기 위해서요
And the other point to make here is that this is showing you GPT tokenizer.
여기서 또 한 가지 중요한 점은 GPT 토큰라이저를 보여드린다는 거죠
There are no hard and fast rules about how Tokenizers should work.
토큰이 어떻게 작동해야 하는지 정해진 규칙은 없어요
In fact, we saw a minute ago that in the early days you used to have tokenizer, that every letter
조금 전에 토큰라이저를 사용하던 초창기를 살펴봤는데요 모든 글자가
would map to one token, and you'll see that different models have different approaches to tokenization.
토큰 하나에 매핑되었죠 모델마다 토큰화에 다른 접근법을 갖고 있었어요
And when we look later at open source, we're going to be getting hands on with a bunch of different
나중에 오픈 소스를 살펴볼 땐 다양한 토큰라이저들을 직접 경험해볼
tokenizers.
거예요
And we're going to explore an interesting property of Llama's tokenizer too.
라마 토큰라이저의 흥미로운 속성도 살펴볼 거예요
So different tokenizers work can work differently.
각각의 토큰이 다르게 작동할 수 있어요
There are pros and cons for having fewer tokens or more tokens.
패가 많거나 적을 때 장단점이 있어요
There's not a single answer that depends on the how many parameters are in the model and how it was
모델에 매개 변수가 몇 개 있고 어떻게 훈련받았는지에 따라 답이 달라지지
trained, and so on.
않아요
But this is a more detailed look at GPT tokenizer, and I hope this has given you some clarity and intuition
이번 시간에는 GPT 토큰마이저를 더 자세히 살펴보고 여러분께 명확함과 직관을 얻으셨길
on what it means to to go from words and characters into the world of tokens.
바랍니다 단어와 글자를 토큰의 세계로 바꾸는 게 어떤 의미인지 말이죠